Previously on Star Trek: Discovery...
With the
Enterprise in Spacedock,
Captain Pike and Discovery's mission
to find any rational explanation
for the seven signals
continues to escape me.
And with it, perhaps, any chance
of a relationship with my brother Spock.
Computer, show me Starfleet's
rendering of the seven signals.
Spock drew these signals
two months before they appeared to us.
It's damn near identical.
Amanda?
I stole
Spock's medical file.
I've been waiting for an
update on my officer, Spock.
Your guy is wanted for murder.
Killed three of his doctors,
then fled the starbase.
I thought that he
had left it in the past,
but it's back.
- What is it?
- Your brother called it the Red Angel.
That vision changed him forever.
It wasn't because of a vision.
- It was because of me.
- What did you do?
I will find him.
No.
I will.
Got it.
After the dark matter hit me...
- It's me.
- I started to see a ghost.
Her name was May, but she's dead. Tilly.
- I am losing, Michael.
- You don't need sickbay.
- You need Stamets.
- We should have results
- in one second.
- There he is.
That's the captain.
That's where he flies.
Just as I suspected.
- You are hosting a eukaryotic organism.
- A fungus?
This might hurt a bit.
Security breach by unknown
alien species in Engineering.
Engage quarantine protocol Alpha-Omega.
Energize.
Teleporter incoming.
- Captain.
- Welcome aboard Discovery, Number One.
The failures cascaded
through all our primaries.
Helm, nav, both impulse and
warp drive. Chief Louvier
has an engineering team
working 'round the clock.
I don't think Enterprise will
ever have a chief engineer
more in love with his ship.
Apparently, Enterprise is the only ship
in the fleet that's had any problems.
You know, he warned me.
The damn holographic comm system.
Tell Louvier to rip
out the entire system.
From now on we'll communicate
using good, old-fashioned view screens.
Truth is I never liked the holograms.
They look too much like ghosts.
He told you I'd say that.
No. I told him.
Cheeseburger. Fries.
Habanero sauce.
You want to order some
lighter fluid with that?
That goes with the shake.
Sorry to keep you in Spacedock.
I've made use of the time, Captain.
You've been looking into the
allegations against Spock.
It's hard to comprehend,
let alone believe,
that he murdered three people
at the psychiatric
facility on Starbase Five.
How's the crew taking it?
They don't know the details.
Only that he's in trouble.
There's something else.
Tell me.
Starfleet's classified
his case Level One.
Line officers don't usually
warrant that kind of scrutiny.
It's unprecedented. Which is
why I've done a little digging.
Sanctioned?
Better you don't know
the answer to that.
Before I look at that,
I need to know why you saw fit
to detour Federation protocols.
Something about this
investigation isn't adding up.
I'm not letting him go without a fight.
As usual, we agree.
Captain Pike to the ready room.
I'm late for a briefing.
I'm glad you came.
I'm sorry you can't stay longer.
Next time.
Be careful, Captain.
You, too, Number One.
We should give it a name.
Other than May.
I know it looks like a blob,
but this is one of the most
sophisticated life-forms
I've ever encountered.
It has sentience, intention.
Tilly, the mycelial network
doesn't just connect life.
It contains it.
It's an incubator.
You mean, like, um... like a home?
I've been wondering why
it appeared to me as May,
which got me thinking about the real May
that I met when I was, um, 14.
I was, um... I was a weird kid.
You know?
Like, not a lot of friends
and nobody who really
believed in me, including me.
But... she did.
She wanted to connect to
me, and she tried so hard.
But I don't really think
I was the friend to her that she needed.
I'm certain
you were much kinder than
you give yourself credit for.
You always are.
Thank you, but...
I didn't even know she died.
I feel like I took her for granted.
That girl who thought I was special.
Oh!
I've cross-referenced what
we're calling the Red Angel
with all known winged
and avian life-forms in the Federation.
So far, I've found nothing.
Sorry.
The universal translator
sometimes has trouble
reconfiguring my
lingual clicks and pops.
My answer to you was, "Nothing
in the known universe. "
Which might suggest it's not a species.
- Maybe one of a kind.
- A mutation.
Well, whatever it is,
figuring out how it's connected
to these signals will
help us identify it.
If only we knew what it needs.
Commander Nhan, USS Enterprise.
Glad to be here.
Welcome back aboard.
Could you pass the salt?
Commander Saru,
can you shed any light?
My apologies.
I woke up this morning fighting
an acute rhino virus.
So you have a cold.
I had a cold last week, which sucked.
Saurian. Six nasal canals.
It happens to the best of us, Linus.
Everyone to your stations.
Detmer, set a course
for 108 mark four. Maximum warp.
Aye, sir.
Mr. Saru, you look like hell.
You've been burning the
candle at both ends lately.
Go get some rest.
As you wish, sir.
Burnham. A word.
I understand your first officer
is on her way to Spacedock.
Was her visit informative?
Number One is very resourceful.
People have a tendency to
end up owing her favors.
She uncovered
some classified information
on Starbase Five.
That is the warp
signature of the shuttle
that Spock stole from
the psychiatric facility.
I put us on an intercept course.
We should reach his position
in the next few hours.
S- Sir,
after everything that's happened,
I need to excuse myself
from seeing Spock.
Not sure I follow.
I don't want to make
things worse for him.
He's a fugitive, whatever
the circumstances.
And as Amanda suggested...
I'm probably the last person
who should insert
themselves into this problem.
I disagree. He is lost, Captain.
You are better suited to help him.
I've thought this through.
Please, trust me.
My abiding trust in you
doesn't eclipse the mission at hand.
Facing whatever happened to Spock,
it's not gonna be easy for any of us.
Reaching him has to be the priority.
Detmer, status?
Something has grabbed
us out of warp, sir.
Speed dropping to sub-light.
- Helm going unresponsive.
- Shields up.
Red alert. Owosekun,
are we talking tractor beam?
More powerful than that, sir.
I'm unable to raise shields.
Preliminary analysis indicates
a multiphasic stasis field.
It's disrupting our shield harmonics.
We're at a full stop, sir.
Whatever has us, w-we're
locked into place.
Like a damn fly in a web.
And there is the spider.
♪
Trailer, Sync and corrections by:kDragon
www.addic7ed.com
Star Trek: Discovery
SO2EO4- An Obol for Charon
Starfleet has never
encountered anything like it.
565 kilometers in diameter
with a mass of 6.39 x 10
to the 20th power kilograms.
It melds organic and nonliving matter.
It's also ancient.
Initial scans put it
at 100,000 years old.
"Organic"?
Are you saying it's
some kind of a life-form?
Maybe it is a damn
spider. I hate spiders.
It is premature to assign
any anthropomorphic
distinction or intent.
As of yet, it hasn't
responded to any hails.
But there is this.
The sphere is vibrating.
The computer extrapolated
what it might sound like
based on the surrounding
ambient radiation.
Well, it has my ship,
and I don't know what
in the hell it wants.
Communicate with it or disable
it. And quickly, please.
Captain Pike.
Saru.
Confirmed.
Did it work?
Yes. I can understand you.
I still can't read my controls.
I think this is Tau Cetian.
Am I the only one who bothered
to learn a foreign language?
I have localized
the backup bridge translator.
For the time being,
everyone who speaks Earth
English can communicate.
The rest of the crew and Discovery’s
computer are another matter.
The bridge may be temporarily
fixed, but the virus will continue
spreading through our comms system.
I can try purging it
from the translator's main interface.
We have to be able to
talk to the computer
and the rest of the
crew to have any chance
of breaking free from
that sphere. Do it.
Yes, sir.
I'll go. You should stay
and monitor bridge stations.
I have placed
all systems on... automatic.
And given our current circumstances,
you will need a translator
just to operate the turbo lift.
Are you sure you can do
this?We are wasting time.
We've run a full diagnostic, Captain,
and this section remains
unaffected by the virus.
I will update you if anything changes.
Thank you, Ensign.
If we can't fly this thing, Commander,
we may have to jump away.
The spore drive will be ready, sir.
Bring the drive online,
and then we'll couple the shunts to me,
in case we've got to skedaddle.
♪ Da, Da, Da, Da, Da, Da. ♪
The universal translator
for this section is no más.
Can I... help you?
Uh, unless you can reroute
the plasma regulator
to silo off the relay junction, then,
uh, no.
You're, um...?
Jett Reno, from the Hiawatha.
I hitched a ride off that asteroid.
Chief engineer sent me to firewall off
the critical propulsion systems.
I didn't realize a greenhouse
could be "critical" or "propulsive,"
but, hmm, what do I know?
I'm just a gear head, not a farmer.
A... farmer.
Oh, please, let us know what
you think, because we care.
You should. Antimatter and dilithium
might be old-school, but
they don't let you down.
Why soar when you can crawl?
You don't know me,
Doc. I'm un-insultable.
Especially by a guy who
thinks he can run a ship
on mushrooms that I pick off my pizza.
Spores are clean, renewable.
Yeah, do they come with house dressing?
Do you have any idea how many planets
have been ruined by dilithium mining?
How many battles were fought
to corner its supply?
Of course you don't.
You're one of those people
who never even consider it.
And you're one of those people
that does the ha-ha jokey thing
and then gets all huffy
and in high dudgeon
when you can't think of a comeback.
Do you have gum?
Grape. I...
You know, it was only a
couple centuries ago that
the Earth nearly choked
to death on pollution.
Then we all woke up,
and within a generation,
everything from a truck to a toaster...
Do you want... Sorry. Sorry
...was covered in solar panels.
Yesterday's solar
panels are today's fungi.
Hmm. I can fix stuff
with duct tape, if you want.
Do you think May had anything
to do with the sphere?
What a giant entity from our universe
and a mycelial species from the network?
Well, they have as much in common
as me and that grease monkey.
I could fix that analogy
with duct tape, too.
____
Burnham to bridge. The
universal translator
is back up and running
ship-wide on all systems.
Saru! What is going on?
This is not just a cold.
No, it is not.
What's that hum?
Get down!
Okay, there's more where that came from.
We've got a hundred-
giga-electron volts
surging through the local relays.
Computer's isolated the compartment
in order to contain the damage.
We've still got our life support.
Yeah, but... it could kill us.
If our oxygen ignites,
we'll cook like french fries.
Well, we could divert
the power to act like a...
- a-a lightning arrestor.
- We could use the door
as a ground.
Then the surge would
dissipate through the frame
of the ship. The question is,
how do we conduct the
surge from there to there?
No, a gas could, once it ionizes.
I infuse the spores with
an argon-xenon mixture
to slow decay.
We could link up the canisters
to contain the gas, our
version of a lightning rod.
That's actually not a stupid idea.
It's my version of the house dressing,
- but it saves your life.
- Huh.
Bridge. What happened?
Did the sphere fire on us?
Negative.
EPS conduits are overloading.
Systems are going haywire.
The virus is spreading.
What is happening to the ship?
- We... have to get to the bridge.
- No, no, no, no, no.
Right now we got to get you to sickbay.
Gas her up.
- Gas transference at 100%.
- You're gonna do that manually?
Uh, yeah, 'cause obviously you're not.
Flick the switch.
Are you okay?
I feel like I've been hit by lightning
for the second time this week.
Reno?
Reno? Reno, are you all right?
Weird... dream.
I was playing drums for Prince,
and there were doves and a parade.
Okeydoke.
Wait.
It's gone.
Tilly!
She won't let...
she won't let go!
She won't let go.
What's happening to him?
I'm hoping Dr. Pollard can tell us.
Well, comms is down, so I need
to see what the situation is
in sickbay, anyway.
Triage plasma
burns on level one.
Send non-critical to sickbay two.
Doctor.
Bring him here.
Elevated heart rate,
spiking adrenal levels,
increased neural activity.
The pain would render the
average humanoid unconscious.
What do we do about those?
Nothing. It is an effect of...
my condition.
Ocular discomfort?
No. Kelpiens can see far deeper
into Th-the light spectrum than humans.
I keep seeing flashes
of ultraviolet light,
invisible to you,
but... quite the opposite
for me. Are these symptoms
common among Kelpiens?
This is pointless. And the ship is being
further immobilized as we waste time.
There is no reason to believe
the sphere is benevolent.
Now, please...
Commander.
Dr. Pollard is trying to help you.
Yes. It is unique to my people,
and it is terminal.
Are you certain?
I have never been more
certain of anything in my life.
When I awoke
in discomfort this morning...
I hoped it was just... a passing cold.
But now I have to face the truth.
I do not understand why...
but I am beginning to think that
the sphere is... is triggering
the Kelpien biological
process known as...
Vahar'ai.
It is the event that signals
when Kelpiens are ready to be...
culled for slaughter by... the Ba'ul,
the predator species on my homeworld
of Kaminar.
But there are no Ba'ul here.
It does not matter.
Kelpien ganglia only enflame
in this manner... as we near our end.
I am a...
a slave to my biology.
We are not gonna let you die.
There has to be something
that we can do.
There is not.
Kelpiens undergoing Vahar'ai
either die in the culling
or... are driven to
madness by the effects
of Vahar'ai. Either way,
death is inevitable.
The mycelial entity
has attached itself to Tilly.
We're trying to free her.
Engineering to bridge.
Engineering to bridge. Come in.
Comms are down.
Along with most of the ship.
Don't feel bad.
I know you have to
keep me in quarantine.
Or us.
I feel a little weird.
I should...
I should be terrified, but I'm not.
May means me no harm.
Are you able to see May again?
How do you know this is benign?
May was scary, and she
was clingy, and she,
like, never shut up, but...
she never hurt me.
She said she had a plan for me.
She said that I was her only chance.
Did you ever think she
was manipulating you?
That's what she said you were
doing... she said that you...
you were trying to
poison me against her.
Okay, if that thing wasn't
freaking me out, she is.
The blob seems to be secreting
a psilocybin hallucinogen
to influence her emotions.
So you're saying
she's on a bad trip?
Or maybe it's just trying
to calm her down so she won't be scared.
Or so she won't fight back?
If Saru thinks
that somehow the...
the sphere triggered Vahar'ai,
maybe escaping its grip would
stop what's happening to him.
The problem is freeing ourselves
before it destroys the ship.
If it wanted to destroy
us, why the slow attack?
It's inefficient, right?
It must need something.
It's taking what it needs.
Without the computer,
all our primary systems begin
to fail, including the warp core.
The EPS grid's unstable,
and it's cutting off
entire sections, including Engineering.
Life support's down to
60%, but who's counting?
It is not logical for a
virus to kill its host.
You're attaching a known medical
diagnosis to an unknown entity.
There may be a way to...
slow the virus.
If we can analyze its properties,
we may be able to develop
digital antibodies.
That could give us back enough
control to break the ship free.
In theory, but it will be
a slow process, like...
army ants eating a water buffalo.
I'm on it. Going to the science lab.
You will need my help.
Saru, Commander
Burnham can handle this.
There's no reason to risk
your health any further.
I am dying, Captain...
but I am most certainly not... dead.
The antibodies
are s-slowing the virus's progress.
Life support at 47%.
You are wondering why
I kept this from you.
You don't have to bear it alone.
How...
do I explain...
to the woman who has fought
over and over for the right
to take her next breath
that I come from a race that submits?
I'm your friend.
There will never be judgment between us.
Well, to my shame...
hiding is my nature.
I have learned multiple languages,
yet never shared my own,
fearful of revealing my own...
alienness.
May I...
request a favor?
Of course.
Anything.
I have kept detailed personal logs
since joining Starfleet.
I would ask you...
to officially catalogue
them, so that when...
General Order 1 no longer
applies to the Kelpiens...
they will know a journey like mine...
is possible.
It
would be my privilege.
Did you record your
life before Starfleet?
Uh, you might say my life began
when I was granted refugee
status by the Federation.
While being processed
at Starbase Seven...
...I saw for the first time
life-forms from across the universe,
some with less than I had,
yet, with a dream
of something better.
I listened.
Every story I heard...
...created... a space inside me
to feel more, to...
love more.
I joined Starfleet
to help those in need
the way I was helped.
You are...
the most empathic soul...
I know.
There was just one...
painful caveat to my signing up.
I
could never return home.
Why?
Oh.
More flashes of ultraviolet light.
They are... growing
in... strength and frequency.
- I'll get something from sickbay.
- No. No.
I will be fine.
The captain asked you
to return to the bridge
as soon as possible.
I can continue the work here.
Spock is still
at maximum warp, Captain.
If we're stuck here much
longer, we're going to lose him.
Reallocate power from the transporters
to long-range sensors.
I don't want to lose
contact with his shuttle.
Even with sensors at
max, we won't be able
- to track him for much longer.
- Contact Engineering.
See if they can reroute
impulse power to the deflectors.
If we can raise
shields, we might be able
to disrupt the stasis field
just enough to break free.
If so, can we jump away?
Negative, sir. We
don't have enough power
to create the necessary hull cavitation.
Comms are still down
in Engineering, sir.
Security protocols are
also malfunctioning,
locking off parts of the ship.
How are we doing, Commander?
The digital antibodies
are doing their job,
but progress is sluggish.
I'm running out of options.
If we lose Spock, we lose
any chance of protecting him.
Permission to go to Engineering.
We can't talk to them here, but maybe
I can help them get power to shields.
Permission granted.
- What's wrong?
- The doors won't open,
- and that thing reattached itself to Tilly.
- Can you detach it?
I could cut it off. She
wouldn't even lose a freckle.
Bad idea.
If it's a symbiote,
removing it might kill her.
Well, thanks for stopping by.
I came to see if we can find a
way to boost power to shields.
No. With the systems fluctuating,
this section is partitioned off.
We can't get to the warp core.
Michael...
I feel really tired.
What is happening?
That blob is sending her
in and out of consciousness.
Why is it doing that to her?
It's not like we can ask it.
Actually, we can.
This is a harmonic interface.
It-it links my neurons
to the mycelial network.
With modification,
it could link May to Tilly's
central nervous system.
Let May speak using Tilly's mouth.
Wait. What did you say?
We're gonna talk to it.
We need it to tell us what it wants.
So do we.
The sphere... it's been
trying to tell us something,
and we haven't been listening.
Well, damn, woman, go!We got her.
Saru,
could the sphere be
trying to talk to us?
Using the virus as a way
to make first contact?
Yeah. Yes, of course.
I've been so blind.
The ultraviolet wavelengths
are repeating, like...
like letters would in...
in a sentence... everywhere.
Okay, Saru. Saru, stop. You're
hurting yourself.
No, no. No.
You called me an "empathic soul,"
and it is true. My ganglia
respond to shifts in my environment,
like an early-warning system.
So it is... it is no coincidence
that I started feeling
sick just before...
the sphere engaged us.
- Why would...?
- I know what it is trying to say.
Not first contact, Burnham.
Last contact.
I think it came to us to die.
May?
Still me.
Signal's piss-poor.
We need to amplify it.
Cortical implant.
What, you're talking about trepanation?
Drilling a hole in her skull? Yeah.
Are you gonna fix her
up with duct tape after?
Maybe. Commander?
I think she's right.
And I think you think that, too.
Then we do this together.
This is all I had laying around.
Please tell me you have a laser scalpel.
No. We're gonna do this old-school.
We need to sterilize that drill bit.
First aid kit's over there.
I was able to raise shields.
We've gained some
ground, but we're still
being held by the stasis field.
Power levels coming and going, Captain.
Security reports two dozen
crew still trapped below deck.
Life support failing.
I'm reading an energy buildup
from inside the sphere.
Spiking 10,000 degrees
Kelvin and rising.
Is it powering up weapons?
Reading no identifiable weapons,
but its internal temperature
is now 20,000 degrees Kelvin.
Divert all non-essential
power to weapons.
Lock on that thing's
radial axis and prepare
to fire photon torpedoes on my order.
Aye, sir. Arming torpedoes.
Captain, hold your fire.
I do not believe the
sphere means us any harm.
All evidence to the contrary.
That thing's about to destroy us.
It's not destroying us, Captain.
It's trying to send us a message.
We received its message.
I'm about to send our reply.
Captain, what if
Vahar'ai, my death process,
was triggered because
the sphere is also dying?
You want to run that by me again?
We Kelpiens have a defining trait
Hard-Wired into our DNA: empathy.
I can feel the sphere reaching out,
trying to share something
before it expires.
Sir, I trust Saru's feelings implicitly.
- That sphere didn't come to attack us.
- Captain,
I believe I have discerned
its means of communication.
Detmer, status on Spock's shuttle?
Exits our sensor range in six minutes.
Once we lose his warp signature,
- we won't be able to reacquire it.
- Set an intercept course.
I want us hauling ass
the second we break free.
Aye, sir.
Keep talking and make it fast.
What if the sphere
was not attacking our
universal translator,
but attempting to teach us its language
because it wants to be remembered,
to preserve its history
using Discovery,
but it cannot unless we
power down and let it in?
That thing snatched us out of
warp and almost gutted the ship.
What if we lower shields,
and that's exactly
what it needs to end us?
Computer, adjust view screen display
to ultraviolet.
That is the light
pattern I have been seeing
everywhere, repeating again
and again, generated
by the sphere's virus.
Computer, run the light pattern
through the universal translator.
Captain, I believe we are looking
at a multitude of languages
so advanced, and knowledge so vast
that it simply overloaded our system.
This sphere is 100,000 years old.
Imagine what it knows, what it's seen.
Captain, this falls under Discovery's
original mission statement
as a science vessel.
Well, I'll be.
An amplified cortical implant.
Hey, kiddo.
What's your favorite song?
What?
Your favorite song...
sing it for me.
♪ Though I'm past one
hundred thousand miles ♪
♪ I'm feeling very still
♪ And I think my spaceship
knows which way to go ♪
♪ Tell my wife I
love her very much ♪
♪ She knows.
May?
You
wanted to talk to me?
Here I am.
What do you want? Who are you?
I'm from a species known as the JahSepp.
We lived harmoniously until an
alien intruder began to arrive
at random intervals,
ravaging our ecosystem irreparably.
So, you came for help
to rid your species
of a destructive alien presence?
You are the destructive alien presence.
The-the... the jumps?
Discovery’s jumps?
I broke through the
confines of the network
to reach you, at great risk.
Risk? You infected my friend.
You don't belong inside of her.
You fly the ship from within
the cube, I can reach you.
In Tilly, I found the memory
of May Ahearn, someone I knew
she'd be sympathetic to,
if given a second chance.
Once she trusted May, I
planned to persuade her
to deliver my message to you.
Oh, I can only ask for your forgiveness.
I knew better.
I know better.
I'll do whatever it takes to fix this.
All I ask is that you let Tilly go.
I can't.
I have other plans for her.
Wrong!Oh. No!
Tilly!
The sphere's
internal temperature is approaching
ten-to-the-sixth-power
Kelvin and rising.
Our weapons will just
disintegrate in that heat.
Solar temperatures.
A sign of core collapse.
Captain, if we are correct,
once the transmission is
complete, the sphere can die
knowing that it will
live on after it is gone.
We can choose to fulfill
our part in its destiny,
or simply let it fade away unremembered.
Spock's shuttle is almost
out of sensor range, sir.
Prepare to lower shields.
If this goes south,
overload the warp core
and eject it at the
sphere on my command.
Even at half the distance,
the blast will decimate it.
When it lets go, we
divert all power to shields
and try to ride the shock
wave to a safe distance.
Assuming it doesn't vaporize us first.
If there's even half a
chance you're correct,
I'm bound by my oath and conscience
not to let it vanish forever.
Commanders, take your stations.
I'll follow your lead.
Lieutenant Detmer, lower shields.
Aye, sir. Shields down.
Bryce,
all channels open. Owosekun,
divert all computing
resources to Communications.
Yes, Commander. Here goes nothing.
Transmission is downloading.
All library computers
are processing at 20% above maximum.
Whatever the sphere is saying,
we're getting all of it.
- How long until it blows?
- Seconds. Power
and energy levels are off the chart.
Detmer, can you put enough
distance between us in time?
Negative, sir. We're still
being locked by the stasis field.
Transmission complete. Detmer,
eject the warp core.
Computer controls not responding, sir.
Detonation confirmed.
Hard astern. Full impulse now.
Ah.
It is so beautiful.
The light is almost like... music.
Yes, it is.
I'm at a loss as to how
we're still alive to see it.
The sphere's stasis
field reversed polarity
a nanosecond before detonation...
and pushed us clear.
Its final act was to save us
so we could tell its story.
Hand me the damn torch.
Tilly.
Breathe. Breathe,
Breathe.
Breathe, breathe. Slow it down.
Breathe. Come on, you're okay.
You're still you.
Tilly.
Slow. Shh.
Stamets
to Burnham. We got Tilly.
She's okay.
Now it is my turn.
Take me to my quarters, please.
I left home with a handful of seeds.
Is this from your homeworld?
It is the blossom that marks the...
the passing of seasons on Kaminar.
Somewhere along the way,
I... I lost who I was.
So focused on being
the best Kelpien in Starfleet.
Defined by my rank
and uniform...
...until that is all I became.
You are wrong.
Look at what you've achieved.
You found yourself among the stars.
You found your bravery.
Your strength.
You've saved so many lives, Saru.
Including mine.
It is time.
In that first drawer, you
will find a Kelpien knife,
a keepsake I use to prune my flowers.
I need you
to... to sever my ganglia
and end my suffering.
I need your help
so that I can die now,
peacefully,
before the pain and
madness overtakes me.
Thank you, Michael.
Do we have to do this?
Is it truly inevitable?
I am sorry.
I know how hard this is for you.
How many people you've already lost.
I would do it myself, but...
I am too weak.
After all this time...
...after everything that we
have been through together...
...I realize now
that you are my family, Saru.
I feel the same...
about you.
You are the only one who knows me.
You replaced the
sister I had on Kaminar.
Siranna.
That knife was hers.
I left her
without so much as a good-bye.
You promise me...
no matter how frightening
or painful it may be...
promise me
you will
mend your relationship with Spock.
If you and I can build
this type of bond,
I'm certain you can
do the same with him.
Please.
I promise.
Good-bye, Michael.
I love you, Saru.
Michael? What is wrong?
I- I bare... I barely touched it.
They fell out on their own.
I... I, uh...
don't understand.
I should be...
Your vital signs
have returned to normal.
How are you feeling?
I have never felt this way before.
Fear has always been the
governing principle of my life.
But now...
it is gone.
More than that, I feel...
...power.
My own power.
Well,
consider yourself certified
for duty, Commander.
Despite speaking 94 languages,
there are times when
words are not enough.
Initial reports
are coming in from the science teams.
The sphere didn't just
give us its language.
We have recorded everything
it has seen and experienced
the last 100,000 years.
Its legacy.
And your legacy has a new chapter.
A new and deeply troubling one.
The Kelpien way of life
has always been oriented toward death
and the role the Ba'ul play in it.
My people call it "The Great Balance. "
It is our central, organizing truth.
But you proved it wrong.
Precisely.
And you asked me before
why I could not go home.
It is because I made a
promise to Captain Georgiou
to uphold General Order 1,
not to interfere with
the destiny of my species.
But now,
knowing that what my people
have accepted as the truth
is a lie?
What does this mean for us?
For my species?
My... my planet?
The war between
the Quaternary star systems
and the Roquar'ri Imperium
lasted a solar cent...
From the sphere?
The computer's translation.
It's like we've found our
galaxy's Dead Sea Scrolls.
Federation scientists will
be studying this for centuries
thanks to you and Saru.
I hope it was worth the cost.
Cost us nothing, sir.
I combed through the
sphere's sensor records
and found the last thing that it saw:
Spock's shuttle.
I was able to track it
beyond our sensor range.
Conn,
Commander Burnham is sending you
the coordinates of Spock's shuttle.
Plot a course, and
don't spare the horses.
Aye, sir.
From now on,
I'll work to keep you clear
about whatever happens
with your brother.
Thank you, Captain, but I
have had a change of heart.
I can't abandon him.
No matter the mistakes that I've made,
I need my brother to know that
I will always be there for him.
No matter what.
We need to close the
door to the network.
Forever.
Just making final calculations.
Hi, hi. Hello? Hello? It's me.
Did you see that?
- See what?
- May.
She was there, and then she was gone.
Um...
...you might still be coming
down off your hallucinogen.
- No, I swear. I swear.
- Yeah.
No, it's natural to be paranoid
in your condition. Something
is not right.
Something's not right.
Hello?
Tilly. Hello?
Tilly. Hello, hello...
Wow.
Have you always been a superior being?
Hi. Hello? Hello?
Because...
the harmonics in your aura...
You know, I was thinking
the exact same thing about your aura.
What's that dust on your face?
...dust on your face?
It's on yours, too.
...yours, too.
That tastes like...
Psilocybin?
It dosed us. It dosed us.
Slap me really hard.
Why'd I do that?
To get me focused enough
to find the med kit.
I need to hit us both
with a shot of impedrizine
so we can come down.
Now I need to give one to Tilly.
Wait a minute. Where is she?
Tilly?
Wait.
Oh, my God, they took her.
No. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Tilly?
No!
Ensign Sylvia Tilly is out there.
And we have an hour to find her.
- You kidnapped me!
- I need your help.
Try not to blow us up.
Don't be so worried.
Burnham to the bridge.
We have a complication.
We wont survive complications.
Trailer, Sync and corrections by:kDragon
www.addic7ed.com
Star Trek: Discovery
SO2EO4- An Obol for Charon